A Guide to the Papers of the Brown and related Bruce, Evans and McIntyre Families 1806, 1854-1988
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Brown and related Bruce, Evans and McIntyre Families 1806, 1854-1988
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10719-c
ca. 440 items (2 Hollinger boxes)
This collection consists of the papers of the Brown, Bruce, Evans, and McIntyre families of central Virginia, Kentucky, and Ohio, chiefly correspondence and genealogical material but also including photographs, printed material, notebooks, newsclippings, and manuscripts.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the Library by Mrs. Emily Brown Carnan of Charlottesville, Virginia, on March 10, 1989.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of the papers of the Brown, Bruce, Evans, and McIntyre families of central Virginia, Kentucky, and Ohio, containing ca. 440 items, 1806, 1854-1988, and undated, chiefly correspondence and genealogical material but also including photographs, printed material, notebooks, newsclippings, and manuscripts.
The correspondence includes that of the Brown family, Milton McIntyre Brown, Eli M. Bruce, and the Bruce family. Topics in the Brown family correspondence includes: Aunt Sallie McIntyre Thompson's death (January 16, 1903); a description of a European trip (July 26, August 12 & 18, and summer 1906); life at Culver Summer Naval School (July 26, August 5 & 13, 1906); the fire at the homeplace, at Glendale, Ohio (March and April 4, 1908); the description of a visit with Milton Brown at his camp just prior to his departure for Europe with the 4th Battalion Commander's Detail of the 83rd Artillery Division (June 10, [1917]); genealogical connections with the Caldwell family (May 5, 1936); the Glendale Centennial (June 5, 1955); and the Civil Rights Bill (June 29, 1964).
Letters from Milton Brown generally are concerned with his activities during World War I. Brown mentions his work for The Commission For Relief in Belgium (May 9, 1916; January 29 March 20, and September 20, 1917); problems with censorship (September 20, 1917); the arrival of his troop transport in France, his attempts to find a river or lake for bathing and fresh food, washing clothes in Brittany, and his work as an interpreter in Battery B., 324th Field Artillery Heavy, American Expeditionary Forces (July 5, 1918); an article concerning the deportation of Belgian workmen, (not present) (August 16, [1918]); living conditions in American bunkers, especially his problem with rats (October 1, 1918); the danger of the soldiers from gas and the response of the men to gas warnings (October 26, 1918); and visit to a Belgian castle (July 28, 1936).
The correspondence of the Bruce family of Maysville, Kentucky, contains typed transcripts of all of the letters except June 4, 1856, and April 4, 1858. Topics include references to the newlyweds, Eli Metcalfe Bruce and Sallie E. Withers, and Sally Bruce and O.H.P. Thomas (March 8 & 9, 1854); a description of the school attended by Elizabeth Morgan Bruce (May 20, 1854); the possible selling of the family farm (October 30, 1855; November 18, 1855; and December 14, 1855); a wedding in which the floor collapsed due to the excessive number of people present (December 14, 1855); and bizarre local deaths and happenings (February 25, 1856).
There are three letters from Eli M. Bruce (1828-1866), a member of the Ways and Means Committee of the Confederate Congress, to his mother, Sabina Metcalf Bruce (1804-1883) present in the collection. These mention his packing house in Chattanooga, Tennessee, and presents for Christmas (December 12, 1862); Bruce's financial resources and his disappointment over the lack of repayment of his many loans (July 20, 1866); and his insistence that his parents use his present of gold for whatever they want (November 9, 1866).
Other notable items in the collection include a commonplace book belonging to Mrs. Harry Whiting Brown; a genealogical notebook concerning the Bruce and related families; genealogical notes about the Ward, Humphreys, Waters, and Whiting families; manuscripts by [Bruce Whiting Brown]; and individual folders devoted to miscellaneous papers concerning Alice Humphreys Brown, the Brown family, Eli Bruce, the Bruce family, Camp Osawa, Pointe au Baril, Ontario, the Evans family (including the Wood family), Glendale, Ohio, and the McIntyre and Withers families.
Photographs include those of the Parton family, Glendale, Ohio, Grandmother Morris, George Stubblefield and Mattie Evans Bruce, camping photographs, the Wagner family, Alice Humphreys Brown, Emily St. Clare Brown, Valerie Holloway, the Brown brothers and their goat cart, Red Rose Troop 44, the Glendale Centennial Celebration, Clare Holloway, St. Clare Morehead Evans Attwell, and Elizabeth Bruce McIntyre.
Arrangement
The material in each folder is arranged chronologically and the folders are in alphabetical order according to the type of material in each (correspondence is filed with the letters). The material was originally arranged by family or individual name and this order has been maintained as much as possible.
Genealogical Notes
A. The Brown Family
Harry Whiting Brown (?-1929) married in 1882 Lucy Chappell McIntyre (1860- ?) and produced the following children:
1) Bruce Whiting Brown (1883-[1966]) m. 1911 Alice Bruce (1892?)-1987
2) Robert Brown (1888-?) m. 1913? Frances Hale Hearn
3) Milton McIntyre Brown (1890-1979) m. 1919 Erica Bunge (1891-1986)
4) Harry Brown, Jr. (1895-?) m. 1918 Beth [?]
5) Edna Brown (1885-1886)
6) Elizabeth Bruce Brown (1898- ?) m. ca. 1917 [?]
B. The Bruce Family
George S. Bruce (1800-1883) m. 1823 Sabina Metcalf (1804-1884) and had the following children:
1) Eleanor Bruce (1827-1851) m. J.A. Chappell (?-1893)
2) Eli Metcalf Bruce (1828-1866) m. Sallie E. Withers Bruce Morris (1835- ?)
3) Sally Bruce (1829-1890) m. 1853 O.H.P. Thomas (1817-1878)
4) Henry Clay Bruce (1831-1916) m. 1858 Susan Stockwell (1838- 1925)
5) William Pickett Bruce (1832-1903) m. 1859 Orra Norvell (1840-1867)
6) Lucy Partes Bruce (1834-1900)
7) Nancy Ewing Bruce (1838-1841)
8) Elizabeth Morgan Bruce (1840-?) m. 1859 C.W. McIntyre (d. by 1902)
9) James Bruce (1842-1849)
10) Martha L. Bruce (1844-?) m. 1870 Frank M. Peale (1842-1924)
C. Children of Bruce W. Brown and Alice Humphreys Bruce:
1) Alice H. Brown (1912-1925)
2) Betty Lou Brown
3) Emily St. Clare Brown Carnan
4) Anne Milton Brown Head
5) Bruce W. Brown, Jr.
6) Lucy Elizabeth Wagner
Contents List
- Commonplace Book Belonging to Mrs. Harry Whiting Brown ca. 1875-1927 (Box 1)
- Genealogical Notebook re the Bruce and Related Families ca. 1902-1913 (Box 1)
- Genealogical Notes re the Ward, Humphreys, Waters, and Whiting Families 1883, 1892, 1937-1943 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Brown Family 1886-1988, n.d. (Box 1)
- Letters from Milton McIntyre Brown 1906-1943, n.d. (Box 1)
- Letters from Eli M. Bruce 1862-1866 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Bruce Family, w/Transcripts 1854-1858, 1897 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Papers ca. 1909-1937, n.d. (Box 2)
- Papers re Alice Humphreys Brown 1912-1926 (Box 2)
- Papers re the Brown Family 1806, 1885-1988 (Box 2)
- Papers re Eli Bruce 1873-1988 (Box 2)
- Papers re the Bruce Family [ca. 1865?]-1988, n.d. (Box 2)
- Papers re Camp Osawa, Pointe au Baril, Ontario 1978-1987 (Box 2)
- Papers re the Evans & Wood Families 1868-1988, n.d. (Box 2)
- Papers re Glendale, Ohio 1913-1987, n.d. (Box 2)
- Papers re the McIntyre & Withers Families 1859-1902 (Box 2)
- Photographs ca. 1875-1975 (Box 2)
- "Some Reminscences of the Old Canal," "My Day That Might Be," and "Lafcadio Hearn Impressionist" by [Bruce W. Brown] n.d. (Box 2)